Guide to the Wladyslaw W. Kulski Papers, 1933-1987 UA.29.02.0084
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wladyslaw W. Kulski papers
1933-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kulski, W. W. (Władysław Wszebór), 1903-1989
UA.29.02.0084
7 Linear Feet
Wladyslaw W. Kulski was born in Warsaw, Poland on July 27, 1903. After earning his doctorate, Dr. Kulski served as diplomat and an educator. He taught Political Science at Duke University from 1964 until his retirement in 1973. He died May 16, 1989. Materials include correspondence, pamphlets, manuscripts, course notes, notebooks, photographs, printed matter and a scrapbook. The collection ranges in date from 1710-1987 and is in English, Polish, French and German.
5000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours notice required for retrieval.
Provenance
The Wladyslaw W. Kulski Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1989.
Biographical/Historical note
Born in Warsaw, Poland on July 27, 1903, Wladyslaw W. Kulski was a diplomat and educator who earned a Master of Law degree in 1925 from Warsaw Law School and a Doctor of Law in 1927 from Paris School of Law. In 1938, he married Antonina Reutt of Kislovodsk, Russia. They had no children. He was a member of the Polish diplomatic service from 1928-1945 and Minister Plenipotentiary, Polish Embassy, London from 1940-1945. Dr. Kulski served as Professor of Political Science at the University of Alabama from 1948-1951, at Syracuse University from 1951-1964, and at Duke University from 1964-1973. He authored several works, including Thus Spake Germany (1941) and The Soviet Regime (1954) and was editor of the Polish "White Book." Dr. Kulski died in Durham, NC on May 16, 1989.
Dr. Kulski began his diplomatic career as a member of the staff of the League of Nations service at the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs (1928-1933). In that position, he functioned as a legal and political officer, was a member of the Polish delegation to the Conference of the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments in Geneva (1932-1933), and was councilor and later Secretary of the Permanent Delegation of Poland to the League. From 1936-1940, he was head of the legal service at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. In 1939, he was sent to London to negotiate the British-Polish Treaty of Mutual Assistance, which soon became the diplomatic basis for Britain's declaration of war on Nazi Germany. In 1940, he became Minister Plenipotentiary at the Polish Embassy in London and held that post until 1945 when he left the Polish service. He came to the U.S. in 1946 and became a naturalized citizen in 1953.
In 1964, he came to Duke University where he was named James B. Duke Professor of Political Science. He retired in 1973. During his academic career, Dr. Kulski continued to lecture to audiences in academia and government. He specialized in comparative government, in particular the Soviet government, international relations, and international law. He was awarded several foreign decorations and held both Fulbright and Guggenheim research awards.
Scope and Contents note
Contains correspondence, diplomatic papers, conference papers, articles, printed matter and other materials related to Dr. Kulski's role as a Polish diplomat before and during World War II and as a lecturer and teacher of Political Science after the war. The materials, approximately half of which are in Polish, pertain to Slavic Studies, Soviet politics and government, and issues in European diplomacy and politics before, during and after World War II. The collection includes hand- and typed-written manuscripts in Polish, English, French and German and materials by and about his brother, Julian E. (1905-1988), including a memoir of Stefan Starzynski, mayor of Warsaw. Also included is the correspondence of Antonina Kulski, largely in Polish with a few in English and French. Her letters that largely cover the Kulski's time in London during World War II and consists of communication with Polish soldiers, namely Kazimierz Domaszewski and Bohdan Brzozowski. There are also some photographs of presumably Polish soldiers during World War II and likely Kulksi family members and friends. There is also a scrapbook of clippings and correspondence. Material ranges in date from 1710-1987, with the bulk covering 1933-1969.
Related Material
Wladyslaw Wszebor Kulski Papers, 1930-1984
Hoover Institution Archives (Stanford, California)
Robert S. Rankin Papers, 1898-1987 (bulk 1927-1976)
Duke University Archives
World War, 1939-1945; Scrapbooks; Diplomatic and consular service, Polish -- Great Britain; Polish language -- 20th century; League of Nations; Kulski, W. W. (Władysław Wszebór), 1903-1989; Kulski, Julian Eugene, 1929-1988; Kulski, W. W. (Władysław Wszebór), 1903-1989
- Wladyslaw W. Kulski, 1710-1987, 3.5 boxes
  - box 1 (Box 1)
    - Collection Inventory (Box 1)
    - Biographical Info, CV, Bibliography, Lecture Announcements (Box 1)
    - Revue de Droit International. 1953: 31(3) (Box 1)
    - Russian Review. 1954-1956, 13(2); 15(3); 15(4) (Box 1)
    - Russian Review. 1959-1960, 18(2); 19(3); 19(4) (Box 1)
    - Russian Review. 1966-1967, 25(3); 25(4); 26(1) (Box 1)
    - Book of Poems by Elizabeth Siedlecki: Steps of a Pilgrim (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, news clippings, 1940-1946 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1959 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Soviet Regime, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Syracuse [University] Press, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Peaceful Co-Existence, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, various, 1949-1964 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
    - Portfolio covers (Box 1)
    - Nazi Propaganda, 1940s (Box 1)
    - "White Book," Manuscript, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - "Ministers Two Spraw Zagranicznyck" and "White Book," 1940 (Box 1)
    - "White Book," General File, 1940 (Box 1)
    - "La Vente Sur les Organies de la Guerre Actuelle," Manuscript, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Outline on "Germany: Eternal Enemy of Europe and of Civilization," 1940s (Box 1)
    - Handwritten Papers (in Polish), 1940s (Box 1)
    - Foreign Ministry, 1940s (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Poems, News Clippings, 1940s (Box 1)
    - "Thus Spake Germany," News Clippings, Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Polish Exhibition, News Clippings, Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Article Manuscripts, Post-1946 (Box 1)
    - Article Manuscripts, 1950s (Box 1)
    - Julian E. Kulski, 1947-1980 (Box 1)
    - Manuscript on the Jagiellonian Library, circa 1957 (Box 1)
    - Social Science Research Council Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Various letters, 1959-1961 (Box 1)
    - Conference Board of Associated Research Councils, Fulbright Award, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Guggenheim and Fulbright correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - Dog pedigree papers, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Trip to Paris, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Paris lectures with news clippings, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Manuscripts, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
    - AAUP article on publishing, circa 1970 (Box 1)
    - Polish Institute of International Affairs, 1974 (Box 1)
  - box 2 (Box 2)
    - Datebooks, 1940-1945 (Box 2)
    - Address book (Box 2)
    - Notebooks: Excerpts from League of Nations, United Nations Declarations and Philosophy, Creative Fiction Excerpts (Box 2)
    - W.W. and Antonina Kulski's Polish Visas, 1933-1939 (Box 2)
    - 1968 Duke Football program (includes article and inserted clipping on Kulski) (Box 2)
    - Kulski articles: Russian Review, 1956-1969 American Journal of International Law, 1950s-1980s Miscellaneous, 1953-1980 (Box 2)
    - Kulski reviews (Box 2)
    - Antonina Kulski's "Christmas in Poland," from Nineteenth Century and After, 1943 (Box 2)
    - Assorted pamphlets, publications (Box 2)
    - Preservation of Principles of Freedom Seminars, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Soviet Treaties of Peace with Italy, Bulgaria, Hungary, Romania, Finland (book), 1947 (Box 2)
    - U.S. Congressional Reports, 1957, 1964 (Box 2)
    - American Slavic and East European Review, 1953: 12(1) (Box 2)
    - Contemporary Review, 1942: 919 (Box 2)
    - Dublin Review, 1943: 426 (Box 2)
    - Foreign Affairs, 1947: 25(4); 1950: 28(4); 1953: 32(1); 1969: 47(2) (Box 2)
    - Journal of Central European Affairs, 1943: 2(4); 1947: 7(3); 1949: 8(4); 1950: 10(1) (Box 2)
    - Modern Age, 1965: 9(3) (Box 2)
    - Nineteenth Century and Afte r, 1941: 129 (770) (Box 2)
  - box 3 (Box 3)
    - Polish Politics, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
    - Retirement, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 3)
    - Julian Kulski, Stefan Starzynski W Mojej Pamiqoi (book), undated (Box 3)
    - Antonina Kulski: Miscellaneous writings, Fiction story, Diary, February 1961, Christmas in Poland manuscript, news clippings, Woman's Outlook, The Dope, Co-operative News, 1940s (Box 3)
    - New York conferences, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Lectures, conferences, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
    - Southern Conference on Slavic Studies, 1970, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Canadian Political Science Association, 1969 (Box 3)
    - NYU Conference on Czechoslovakia, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Foundation for Foreign Affairs Conference, 1965 (Box 3)
    - University of Pennsylvania Conference, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Bernard Fall memorial service, speech, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Emory University Conference on communism, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Hoover Institution Conference, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Seminars, Political Science 360; NC Conference, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Vanderbuilt University lectures, 1964; Television Notre Dame, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Lectures, 1964-1983 (Box 3)
    - Course materials, PS 165, undated (Box 3)
    - Course materials, PS 198, student paper on "The French Socialist Party," 1966 (Box 3)
    - Course materials, PS 225, undated (Box 3)
    - Course materials, PS 360, undated (Box 3)
    - Course materials, Seminar on International Relations, undated (Box 3)
    - Course materials, PS 145, Soviet Politics, circa 1964 (Box 3)
  - box 4 (Box 4)
    - Photocopied miscellaneous pamphlets, undated (Box 4)
    - Manuscript Actum in Castro Bedgo, 1710 (Box 4)
    - Statute: Swiatowego Zwiazku Polakow Z Zagranicy (Constitution of the International League of Poles Abroad), 1936 (Box 4)
    - The Bulletin (German), 1971-1973 (Box 4)
    - Pamphlets: Hexology and Among the Amish, 1960s (Box 4)
    - Pamphlet: Uniwersal O Podwodach, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Pamphlet: Library of J.G. Herder Institute in Marburg, undated (Box 4)
    - Tito Speaks, magazine article, 1940s (Box 4)
    - 18th century French manuscript facsimiles (including Rousseau) (Box 4)
    - News clippings, 1940s-1960s (Box 4)
    - Reviews of Kulski's books (Box 4)
- Antonina Kulski, 1939-1974, 1.5 boxes
  - box 4 (Box 4)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 4)
  - box 5 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 5)
    - Postcards, 1940-1952 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Concert programs, transcript, miscellaneous writings, circa 1960s (Box 5)
    - University of Alabama notebooks: Rousseau, Rousard, undated (Box 5)
    - University of Alabama notebooks: Old French, Rabelais, undated (Box 5)
    - University of Alabama notebook: Montaigne, undated (Box 5)
    - University of Alabama term papers: Montaigne, Rabelais, undated (Box 5)
    - University of Alabama term papers: Polish government, French, de Staël, undated (Box 5)
    - University of Alabama term papers: Bourget, Roussard, Voltaire, undated (Box 5)
    - Antonina Kulski's Christmas in Poland, from T he Nineteenth Century and After, 1943 (Box 5)
    - The Tomb of Agamemnon, translated from Polish by Antonina Kulska, printed in The Nineteenth Century and After, 1944 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1961 February (Box 5)
    - Christmas in Poland (Box 5)
    - The Dope, Comparative News, Woman's Outlook, 1940s (Box 5)
- Oversize, 1 boxes
  - box 6 (Box 6)
    - Photograph: Antonina Kulski, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Large newspaper clippings, 1940s-1980s (Box 6)
    - Assorted magazines, pamphlets (mostly Polish), 1930s-1980s (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook of news clippings, correspondence (Box 6)
    - Cardboard mailing roll: 1790s Japanese print (Box 6)